{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The last colonial mayor of New York City, David Matthews, was accused of kidnapping a politician with this surname who, alongside William Smith, Jr. and John Morin Scott, was part of \"The Triumvirate.\" The first governor of New Jersey had this surname, as did a man who drafted the Declaration of Independence alongside Jefferson, Franklin, Adams, and Sherman. That politician with this surname worked with Robert Fulton on the first steamboat from Clermont Manor. For ten points, give this surname of \"The Chancellor\" who negotiated the Louisiana Purchase as Minister to France.",
      "answer": [
        "Livingston",
        "Robert Robert Livingston",
        "William Livingston"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a public lecture, this man erroneously called Mario Vargas Llosa [[YOH-sah]] a \"Colombian Nobel Laureate\" despite neither designation being correct. This man's wife, Marta Sahagún [sah-hah-GOON]], was outed for diverting public lottery funds to her private charity. This man, who called Donald Trump's proposed border wall a \"Racist Monument\" on Twitter, faced controversy for calling his opponent, Francisco Labastida, a \"crossdresser.\" The sixty-year dominance of the PRI party was broken by, for ten points, what winner of the 2000 Mexican presidential election and leader of the National Action Party?",
      "answer": "Vicente Fox Quesada"
    },
    {
      "question": "St. Lubinus names a vestigial chapel below the ground of a building in this city, a predecessor of which was destroyed by Danish pirates. Cnut the Great helped fund the construction of a building in this city overseen by Bishop Fulbert. Henry Adams wrote about a building in this city containing over 170 stained glass windows. That building in this city, south of Paris, contains an early instance of the Flamboyant style and the external use of flying buttresses. For ten points, name this French city which is home to a noted namesake Gothic cathedral which contains the Black Madonna.",
      "answer": [
        "Chartres ]",
        "Chartres Cathedral",
        "Cathedral of Our Lady of Chartres 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This event's instigator claimed, “The time is now, the fifth month when the rain falls.” Contrary to myth, only the main hall was set aflame during this event, plans for which were announced at a renga poetry session. Mori Ranmaru dutifully carried out the instructions of one figure involved in this event, the instigator of which was killed while fleeing the Battle of Yamazaki. This event was carried out by Akechi Mitsuhide, who was subsequently defeated by Toyotomi Hideyoshi. For ten points, name this incident in which the first \"Great Unifier\" of Japan was killed.",
      "answer": "Death of Oda Nobunaga"
    },
    {
      "question": "This work notes that the arrival of refugees in Europe led to a “great shock.\" \"Reflections on the Hungarian Revolution” are included in the fourteenth chapter of this work, which is divided into essays including “Imperialism” and \"Antisemitism.” The central concept of this work is contrasted with despotism and tyranny in that the aforementioned systems limit terror to political dissidents only. For ten points, name this first major book by Hannah Arendt, which examines a form of government associated with Nazism and Stalinism.",
      "answer": "The Origins of Totalitarianism"
    },
    {
      "question": "This pitcher had a perfect game in which the opposing pitcher, Bob Hendley, only allowed one hit. Nolan Ryan’s 383-strikeout season surpassed the previous record held by this man, who made a decision that resulted in Don Drysdale pitching the opening game of the 1965 World Series. That event prompted a remark during a Heritage Month event in which Barack Obama noted his own inability to pitch. This man sat out the first game of that World Series in observance of Yom Kippur. For ten points, name this legendary left-handed pitcher for the Dodgers nicknamed “Sandy.”",
      "answer": [
        "Sandy Koufax or Sanford Koufax",
        "Sanford Braun"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One figure at this battle was killed while slashing his sword and yelling, “Surrender, you traitors!” The Illinois Monument formed the basis of the National Park at this battlefield. Cheatham Hill was the site of a bloody charge led by George Thomas during this battle which was won by Joseph Johnston's forces who were set up around Rocky Face Ridge. Occurring during William Tecumseh Sherman’s Atlanta campaign, this battle inspired the name of the first MLB commissioner. For ten points, name this Civil War battle fought around a namesake northern Georgia mountain.",
      "answer": "Battle of Kennesaw Mountain"
    },
    {
      "question": "The orator of this speech claimed, “Never has a lawyer had to practice his profession under such difficult conditions.” This speech asks, “What law and what justice?” and notes that its speaker has been held in solitary confinement for a period of 76 days. Delivered in 1953, this oration's speaker was a member of the Orthodox Party and was charged for his part in a raid on the Moncada Barracks in an attempt to overthrow Fulgencio Batista. For ten points, name this speech by Fidel Castro claiming that future generations would forgive him.",
      "answer": [
        "History Will Absolve Me speech or La historia me absolverá",
        "\"History will definitely tell it all\"",
        "or \"historia definitivamente va a revelar todo\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "General Gilbert Diendéré led a failed 2015 coup in this country, where Christophe Dabiré [[dah-bee-REH]] resigned as prime minister in December 2021. After January 2022, this country was led by members of the Patriotic Movement for Safeguard and Restoration, whose actions led to this country being suspended from ECOWAS. For ten points, name this West African country where President Roch Kaboré of the People's Movement for Progress was ousted in a coup led by Colonel Paul-Henri Damiba in Ouagadougou.",
      "answer": "Burkina Faso"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an epic poem involving members of this ethnic group, a cyclops-like figure named Goggle-Eye is born to a peri spirit and a human father. That work about this ethnic group focuses on a soothsayer and storyteller given a title translating to “Grandfather.” The Book of Dede Korkut is a work focusing on members of this ethnic group, which ruled an empire that produced the Book of Government. That book was written by the Persian vizier Nizam al-Mulk, who was employed by a member of this ethnic group named Alp Arslan. For ten points, name this ethnic group of the Oghuz and Seljuks.",
      "answer": [
        "Turks",
        "Turkic",
        "or Turkish",
        "Oghuz Turks",
        "Seljuq Turks 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man depicted a mass grave for tenement residents in his The Trench in Potter's Field. This activist documented street gangs in photos such as Bandit's Roost, collected in a popular book. A member of the \"Good Movement\" named Lawrence Veiller worked with this man to promote “model tenements.” Mulberry Street was a common setting for the best- known works of this man, who used cartridges and flash powder as part of a New York City muckracking effort. For ten points, name this photojournalist of How the Other Half Lives.",
        "answer": "Jacob August Riis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A similar book documenting \"Poverty in America,\" The Other America was written by what social activist and founding member of the Democratic Socialists of America?",
        "answer": "Michael Harrington or Edward Michael Harrington Jr."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, one figure claimed, \"All day long, I will never cease to settle here, there, and everywhere” and claimed that material wealth was reserved for the righteous. Lots were used to pick the dikasts during this event, in which the concept of asebeia [[ah-seh-BEE- ah]] was central. An inner daimon allegedly prevented the unethical activity of a figure in this event who compared himself to a gadfly. Following this event, its central figure drank hemlock. For ten points, name this event in which charges of “corrupting the youth” were leveled against a Greek philosopher.",
        "answer": [
          "Trial of Socrates",
          "descriptive answers that also include information of the charges levelled against Socrates"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Platonic dialogue involves Socrates’s discussion of the nature of justice with a namesake native of Alopece [[ah-loh-PEH-kay]] while Socrates waits in prison?",
        "answer": "Crito"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s Aplerbeck Hospital was a transfer point for mentally disabled individuals being sent to Hadamar to be euthanized in the T4 program. Up to 25,000 people were employed at the Westfalenhütte [[vest-FAH-len-hoo-tuh]] in this city, an industrial site that was among the key targets of an Allied bombing campaign. This was the largest city targeted in a campaign by Raymond Poincaré [[pwahn-kah-REH]] to limit the coal and steel output of its central nation. For ten points, name this largest city in the Ruhr and site of a “Borussia” football team.",
        "answer": [
          "Dortmund",
          "Tremonia",
          "Duorpm"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "An Allied air raid destroyed the central railway station in Dortmund which, like those of many other German cities, was referred to by this German word.",
        "answer": "Hauptbahnhof ] 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two years prior to this conflict, its parties signed a “seven-point agreement” which prohibited one side from searching civilian vehicles. Wasfi Tal was assassinated following this conflict, in which one side was allied with Pakistan’s Muhammad Zia-ul-Haq. A strip of land near Zarqa was the site of a hijacking during this conflict involving the fedayeen of a group who relocated following Israel’s acquisition of the West Bank. The forces of King Hussein won this year-long conflict against the PLO. For ten points, name this civil war primarily fought in Jordan.",
        "answer": "Black September"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "King Hussein was a monarch from what royal family of Jordan that formerly ruled Hejaz, Syria, and Iraq? This family of Mecca revolted against the Ottomans with the assistance of Lawrence of Arabia.",
        "answer": [
          "House of Hashim Code name",
          "exact date and location required. An X-shaped pattern was created as part of this attack, which targeted an area that was particularly vulnerable in the aftermath of a 1923 earthquake. M-69s were dropped in working-class neighborhoods as part of this campaign, which began two years after the far less-lethal Doolittle Raid targeted its central city. For ten points, napalm was used extensively during what campaign that led to the burning of an Asian capital? ANSWER: Bombing of Tokyo on 10 March or Firebombing of Tokyo on 10 March",
          "Tōkyōdaikūshū",
          "Operation Meetinghouse",
          "Great Tokyo Air Raid",
          "but"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A deity popularly worshipped in Palmyra who represented this thing was Malakbel. A Lithuanian feast worshiping this thing, under the name Saule, was converted into St. Jonas's Festival. The Quran chastises the subjects of the Queen of Sheba for worshipping this entity, one representation of which was given elevated status under Aurelian’s reign. A barge was used every night by an Egyptian deity representing this entity. The title “Invictus” was given to a god representing this object in Rome. For ten points, Ra represented what heavenly entity?",
        "answer": [
          "Sun",
          "Sol before “solar” is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Roman emperor and priest of a namesake sun deity was lambasted by ancient sources for marrying a Vestal Virgin and completely disregarding issues of state.",
        "answer": "Elagabalus or Heliogabalus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After one event, this man told Hamar Greenwood, “You had us dead beat. We could not have lasted another three weeks.” This man ordered the killing of a group whose service in the Middle East inspired its name, the Cairo Gang. This man claimed to have “signed [his] actual death warrant” after negotiating what he believed was \"the freedom to achieve freedom” with David Lloyd George. Arthur Griffin signed that treaty with this man the year before an incident in County Cork in 1922. For ten points, name this pro-treaty revolutionary who was assassinated during the Irish Civil War.",
        "answer": "Michael Collins or Mícheál Ó Coileáin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Michael Collins was elected as a representative to what revolutionary parliament that lasted from 1919 to 1922? After recognition from Britain, it was replaced by the Oireachtas [[or-AHK-tahss]].",
        "answer": [
          "Dáil Éireann or Revolutionary Dáil",
          "First Dáil",
          "or Second Dáil"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The last scene this actor ever filmed is nicknamed the “Last Supper,” as it portrays him making a drunken speech alone at a table. While in New York, this actor landed roles on Broadway in plays such as See the Jaguar and The Immoralist. This actor remains the only person to receive two posthumous Academy Award acting nominations. With only three films to his credit, for ten points, what actor starred in East of Eden, Rebel Without a Cause, and Giant before dying at age 24?",
        "answer": "James Dean or James Byron Dean"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Giant starred both James Dean and which actor, who also appeared in a 1967 war film loosely based on the 1941 Allied attempt to take Tobruk? This man died of AIDS complications in 1985.",
        "answer": "Rock Hudson or Roy Harold Scherer, Jr. 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this empire donated a cloak, which had allegedly belonged to Muhammad, to the Kirka Sharif. This empire acquired land north of the Sutlej River after defeating Sadashiv Rao Bhau at the Third Battle of Panipat. A loya jirga coronated the founder of this empire, Ahmed Shah. This state conquered Mashad from the Afsharid Dynasty and sacked Mughal-era Delhi before withdrawing to the western side of the Indus. For ten points, name this eighteenth-century Middle Eastern power, ruled by the namesake Afghan dynasty.",
        "answer": [
          "Durrani Empire or Durrani Dynasty",
          "Sadozai Kingdom",
          "Afghan Empire before \"Afghan\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The earlier Second Battle of Panipat was a victory for which Mughal emperor over Hemu Khan?",
        "answer": "Akbar the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nilus of Sora supported attempts by this man to secularize land belonging to monasteries. A regulation on legal fees was among the centralizing reforms put forth by the Sudebnik passed during the reign of this man. Philotheus [[fee-loh-THEH-ooss]] wrote a letter to this man claiming that the domain he ruled was the Third Rome. This man faced Akhamat Khan at a battle known as the Great Stand on the Ugra River. In 1480, the Golden Horde was defeated by this man who led efforts to renovate the Kremlin. For ten points, name this Grand Prince of Moscow.",
        "answer": [
          "Ivan III of Russia",
          "Ivan III Vasilyevich",
          "Ivan the Great"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ivan III married a princess who was a member of this Byzantine royal family whose reign ended with the 1453 Fall of Constantinople.",
        "answer": [
          "Palaeologus",
          "Palaiologos",
          "Palaiologina",
          "Palaeologue"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Articles of Confederation",
      "prompt": "Concerning the United States under the Articles of Confederation, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President of the Congress, known for his large signature on the Declaration of Independence.",
          "answer": "John Hancock"
        },
        {
          "question": "Minister of Foreign Affairs who later served as the first Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "John Jay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolt in Western Massachusetts which influenced the adoption of the Constitution in favor of the Articles.",
          "answer": "Shays' Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ivy league school whose Nassau Hall served as headquarters of the 4th Confederation Congress.",
          "answer": "Princeton University"
        },
        {
          "question": "1783 conspiracy by disgruntled soldiers after the Congress gave them underfunded pensions.",
          "answer": "Newburgh Conspiracy"
        },
        {
          "question": "1780s Company, co-founded by George Washington, which aimed to improve the navigability of the title Mid-Atlantic river.",
          "answer": "Potomac Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Merchant and Superintendent of Finance who established the Bank of North America.",
          "answer": "Robert Morris, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Standing army primarily tasked with protecting the frontier.",
          "answer": "First American Regiment 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Daily Life in Sparta",
      "prompt": "Concerning Spartan life, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Mythic hero and son of Zeus from whom the kings claimed to have descended.",
          "answer": [
            "Heracles",
            "Hercules"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Serf class derived from conquering neighboring regions.",
          "answer": "Helots or Heílotes"
        },
        {
          "question": "King who died holding off a large Persian army at Thermopylae.",
          "answer": "Leonidas I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Metal supposedly used as currency instead of gold and silver to prevent hoarding.",
          "answer": [
            "Iron",
            "Ferrum",
            "or Fe"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Festival for a god of shepherds during which they did not make war.",
          "answer": [
            "Karneia",
            "Apollo Karneios"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Council of five \"overseers\" who acted as ambassadors for the state.",
          "answer": "Ephors"
        },
        {
          "question": "Extension of the Agoge [[ah-GOH-geh]] child-rearing system that may have doubled as a state secret police force.",
          "answer": "Krypteia or Krupteia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-citizen class who participated in commerce and manufacturing, unlike full citizens.",
          "answer": [
            "Perioeci or Perioikoi",
            "\"Those dwelling around\"",
            "be generous on pronunciation 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Sejong the Great",
      "prompt": "Concerning Sejong the Great, the ruler of the Kingdom of Korea, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city whose palatial complex he expanded.",
          "answer": [
            "Seoul",
            "Seoul Special City",
            "Hanseong"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion originating in India that he suppressed by banning monks.",
          "answer": [
            "Buddhism",
            "Buddhists",
            "Mahayana Buddhism",
            "or any specific school like Seon",
            "Gyo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty of his which dominated Korea for five centuries.",
          "answer": [
            "Joseon Dynasty",
            "Choson Dynasty"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "System of writing he is credited with inventing.",
          "answer": [
            "Hangul",
            "Chosŏn'gŭl"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancestors of the Manchu whom he aimed to conquer during the Songhua River Campaign.",
          "answer": "Jurchens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island targeted by the Gihae Expedition, which aimed to dislodge the Wokou Pirates.",
          "answer": "Tsushima Island"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of his who abdicated in an effort to guide his early rule.",
          "answer": "Taejong"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kind of device, exemplified by the Cheugugi [[choo-GOO-gee]], invented by the Academy of Science to assist agriculture.",
          "answer": [
            "Rain Gauge",
            "Udometer",
            "or Pluviometer",
            "or Ombrometer",
            "or Hyetometer",
            "descriptive answers of instruments intended to measure precipitation 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Though he was never Speaker, this politician served as Dean of the House of Representatives after Sam Rayburn. With Park Trammel, this politician named a bill that authorized the creation of new warships. Considered the “Father of the Two-Ocean Navy,\" (20 pts)",
        "this politician had the rare honor of having an aircraft carrier named after him while he was still alive. A landmark in the Ellsworth Mountains is also named after this Georgia congressman and is the southernmost of the Seven (10 pts)",
        "Summits. For ten points, name this ally of William Halsey and namesake of the highest peak in Antarctica."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Carl Vinson",
        "Vinson‐Trammel Act",
        "USS Carl Vinson",
        "Vinson Massif"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Historian Frank Tipton said of this man, “What would have happened had his father died sooner or if he himself lived longer?” This man asked, “Why did Bergmann put his finger in my throat?” after the doctor misplaced a cannula during an operation. The Antisemitic (20 pts)",
        "Petition was denounced by this man as a “shameful blot on our time.” Married to the eldest child of Prince Albert (10 pts)",
        "and Queen Victoria, for ten points, what German emperor succeeded his father, William I, and had a reign of only 99 days in the Year of the Three Emperors?"
      ],
      "answer": "Frederick III or Friedrich III"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A “struggle” for one field between this thinker and Karl Popper was analyzed by Steve Fuller. In his book The Essential Tension, this man analyzed several “Concepts of Cause in the Development of Physics.” This man is best-known for a work that notes how the process of “puzzle-solving” (20 pts)",
        "is an integral portion of the “normal” part of one field’s development, which is punctuated by events like the Copernican Revolution. That book by this man put forth the idea of the (10 pts)",
        "“paradigm shift.\" For ten points, name this U.S. philosopher who wrote The Structure of Scientific Revolutions."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Thomas Kuhn or Thomas Samuel Kuhn",
        "Kuhn vs. Popper: The Struggle for the Soul of Science"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A disruption of fuel supplies during this period led to Operation Drumstick, which was a plan for Her Majesty's Armed Forces to replace striking Lorry drivers. The headline \"Crisis? What Crisis?\" was employed by the newspaper The Sun to mock the (20 pts)",
        "Prime Minister during this political period. Near the end of this political era, James Callaghan lost a vote of no confidence by one vote, dissolving his cabinet. A Shakespearian (10 pts)",
        "phrase names, for ten points, what late 1970s period of British history characterized by strikes which paved the way for Thatcherism?"
      ],
      "answer": "Winter of Discontent"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's forces were ordered to club the party of Piet [[PEET]] Retief's delegation to death and plunder his laagers in an 1838 massacre. This man executed his chief advisor, Ndlela, by slow strangulation with a cow hide garment. Following (20 pts)",
        "mass desertion at the Battle of Maqongqo [[mah-KOHNG-koh]], this ruler was overthrown by his Boer-backed brother, Mpande [[mah-PAHN-deh]]. Losing the Battle of Blood (10 pts)",
        "River, for ten points, who was this Zulu king who assassinated his half-brother, Shaka?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Dingane or Dingane ka Senzangakhona Zulu",
        "Dingaan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A novel about an author’s experiences at this location includes one character's attempt to identify the “Veiled Lady.\" The Harbinger was a publication run from this place that espoused the ideas of Charles Fourier [[foor-YEH]]. Originally a joint stock company, this place was founded by Sophia and (20 pts)",
        "George Ripley, the latter of whom was a Unitarian Minister. The Blithedale Romance was inspired by its author's experience at this place, which was closely associated with (10 pts)",
        "transcendentalism. Nathaniel Hawthorne was a founder of, for ten points, what experimental \"Farm\" in Massachusetts?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Brook Farm",
        "Brook Farm Institute of Agriculture and Education",
        "or Brook Farm Association for Industry and Education"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2021, prison sentences handed out during this \"Operation\" were the subject of a called-for nullification by Judge Edson Fachin [[fah-KEEN]] due to presiding judge Sérgio Moro's bias during proceedings. This \"Operation,\" which takes its name from the service (20 pts)",
        "station where it was first uncovered, led to the tanking of President Dilma Rousseff's popularity due to her being on the board of the namesake oil company. A money laundering scheme within (10 pts)",
        "Petrobras was revealed in, for ten points, what \"Operation\" that led to the rise of Jair Bolsonaro?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Operation Car Wash",
        "Operação Lava Jato"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist decorated the Duomo with a portrait of an English mercenary on horseback in Funerary Monument to Sir John Hawkwood. Vasari noted how this artist stayed up late in an attempt to find an exact vanishing point, which he explored in his The Hunt in the Forest. (20 pts)",
        "This artist depicted Micheletto da Cotignola [[koh-teen-OH- luh]] and Niccolo da Tolentino in a set of three paintings depicting a 1432 battle between Florentine and (10 pts)",
        "Sienese forces. For ten points, name this Renaissance artist of The Battle of San Romano."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Paolo Uccello",
        "Paolo di Dono 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Père Louis Bazin [[bah-ZAHN]] recorded the death of this ruler, who was surprised in his sleep by conspirators at Quchan [[KOO-chahn]]. A form of artillery known as the zamburak was employed at a victory for this man over Muhammad Shah. This man's tribe in Khorasan (20 pts)",
        "informed the name of his dynasty, the Afsharids. The Battle of Karnal was won by this man, who conducted a number of beheadings along the Yamuna River and took the Peacock Throne (10 pts)",
        "as loot during a campaign against the Mughals. For ten points, name this “Persian Napoleon” who sacked Delhi."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nadir Shah",
        "Nader Qoli Beyg",
        "Tahmāsp Qoli Khan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Carl Hines called for a requirement to replace a word in this song with the word “people” every time it is sung in a certain legislature. This song inspired the original working title of Gone with the Wind, which was “Tote the Weary Load.” Originally named after (20 pts)",
        "“Poor Uncle Tom” from Harriet Beecher Stowe’s best-known novel, this song's lyrics may have been inspired by visits to the Federal Hill plantation. Naming a state park in Bardstown (10 pts)",
        "centered on Senator John Rowan's home, for ten points, what is this state song of a certain commonwealth?"
      ],
      "answer": "\"My Old Kentucky Home, Good-Night!\" 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    }
  ]
}